Guide to the Allan Moll broadcast radio audio collection 1945-1966
Multimedia Archives, J. Willard Marriott Library, University of Utah
Allan Moll broadcast radio audio collection
1945-1966
University of Utah Libraries, Special Collections Audio-Visual Archives J. Willard Marriott Library Special Collections 295 South 1500 East Salt Lake City, Utah 84112-0860 (801) 581-8864
A0561
Moll, Allan, 1922-
42 reel-to-reel audio tapes, 18 phonograph records and 3 audiocassettes
The Allan Moll broadcast radio audio collection (1945-1966) consists of recordings of interviews and news reports compiled by Moll during his time at Los Angeles radio stations KLAC and KHJ as well as Utah's KDYL. Subjects include the 1964 elections, other national issues, Hollywood and local California and Utah news stoires. Moll is the reporter or interviewer on the majority of the recordings. Minnesota native Allan Moll was a radio broadcaster in California and worked for Utah's KDYL radio and Channel 4 television at the beginning and end of his career, respectively.
Biographical Note
Allan Moll (b.1922) was born 13 June in St. Paul, Minnesota. He moved to Salt Lake City, Utah in 1934. Moll began his broadcasting career with KDYL Radio in 1941. During World War II, Moll served in the United Sates Army Air Corps from 1942 to 1945. When he returned, he went to the University of Utah law School and graduated in 1951. Moll worked as Public Affairs Director for Los Angeles radio stations KLAC from 1957 to 1960 and KHJ from 1960 to 1968. Moll worked as a news anchor on Salt Lake City's Channel 4 from 1965 to 1976. He also ran as the democratic candidate for Salt lake County Attorney. Moll has received several awards including: "Outstanding Lawyer of the Year" from the Utah State Justice Court Association, "Outstanding Lawyer of the Year" from the Brigham Young University Political and Legislative Association, and "Broadcaster of the Year" from the Utah Radio and Television Association. He is now retired.
The Allan Moll broadcast radio audio collection (1945-1966) consists of recordings of interviews and news reports compiled by Moll during his time at Los Angeles radio stations KLAC and KHJ as well as Utah's KDYL. Subjects include the 1964 elections, other national issues, Hollywood and local California and Utah news stoires. Moll is the reporter or interviewer on the majority of the recordings. California recordings are on reel-to-reel audiotape and the older Utah recordings are on radio transcription discs.
The materials are arranged by format type. Phonograph records from Moll's early Utah career follow reel-to-reel audiotapes from his California years. Items from the 2004 addendum are listed at the end of the register.
Materials must be used on-site; no use of original material, access copies will be made available for viewing. Five business days advanced notice required. Access to parts of this collection may be restricted under provisions of state or federal law, condition of the material, or by donor.
See also the Allan Moll papers (Accn 1716).
Political campaigns; Election Day; Radio broadcasters; Journalism; Sound Recordings; Sound recordings
- Viewpoint Los Angeles: interview with Robert Kendall, 1965 February 28; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 1)
  Allan Moll interviews Robert Kendall who is the Author of White Teacher in a Black School, also known as, Don't Say Nigger. In this interview, Kendall reveals the lack of support that the faltering school system offers African American Schools. He also condemns the school system for lowering the standard of education among African American communities, which then limits their realm of possibilities.
- Soundtrack pieces for a film about Henry Cabot Lodge running for president, 1964 May 04; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 2)
  An unedited short discussion of the candidates for the 1964 elections as well as the prerecorded opening and closing statements by Allan Moll for an interview with David Goldberg who was the Field Director of the National Draft Lodge Commity.
- 1964 elections - primary elections, 1964 June 02; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 3)
  First a brief address from a few candidates for the 1964 elections. These candidates include Ronald Reagan, Henry Salvatori, Senator Barry Goldwater, and Governor Nelson Rockefeller. Following this, Allan Moll interviews George McClain, a Democratic candidate for the United States Senate, Bill Taylor for the Communist Campaign, Judge Younger running for District attorney and Senator Kiko who comments on the variation in the tabulation of votes. Throughout this report, there are announcements of telephonic surveys as well as reviews of snap tallies, which are then discussed briefly.
- Interview with an unnamed woman, 1963 November 01; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 4)
  This is an interview with a woman from Europe during World War II. She briefly speaks of the importance of overcoming Communism as well as her thoughts on Americas' decision to remain neutral until 1942.
- Special assignment: November 3 1964 ballot, 1964 August 28; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 5)
  This is the third radio show out of a series of five in which the pros and cons of various propositions appearing on the November 3, 1964 ballot are discussed. The propositions discussed here were two of the most controversial propositions, fifteen and seventeen. Proposition fifteen deals with paid television verses free television while proposition seventeen deals with railroad train crews declaring state policy on manning trains.
- In search of a solution: civil rights, 1964 September 13; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 6a-b)
  a) In search of a solution to the civil rights crisis of 1964, the Public Affairs Department of RKO General Broadcasting interviewed twenty-six leaders of thought and action as part of a national symposium. Each of these leaders present their various ideas for resolving the civil rights crisis peacefully and justly. The twenty-six leaders interviewed include: Governor Nelson Rockefeller, Mr. A. N. Sonnabend, Senator Jacob Javits, Malcolm X, Francis Cardinal Spellman, Reverand Dan Potter, Gus Tyler, Will Maslow, George Wallace, Leo Perlis, Stanley Lowell, Judah Cahn, Roy Wilkens, Benjamin Epstein, Reverend Sturgis Riddle, John Slawson, Frank H. Karelsen, Max J. Rubin, Hyman Bookbinder, Representative John Lindsey, Senator Allan Ellendar, Senator Pat McNamara, Senator Thomas Dodd, Senator Clifford Case, Representative Emmanuel Celler, and Senator Kenneth Keating.
  b) This Audiotape contains all of the opening and closing statements for the interviews conducted by Allan Moll.
- Interview with Goodwin Knight, 1964 February 26; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 7)
  In this interview Goodwin Knight, former layer as well as former Judge and Governor of the state of California, discusses legal insanity, capital punishment, and unwritten law. Mr. Knight explains the nature of appeals and briefly describes his personal experiences with granting clemency along with his opinion on how fair of a trial a public defender can give.
- Goldwater nomination announcement, 1964 January 03; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 8)
  Barry Goldwater announces to the public that he will seek the republican presidential nomination for two main reasons; his personal beliefs coincide with millions of other Americans and there where no other republican candidates with a declaration of conscience or political position that would offer the American people a clear choice. He then takes questions from the media. These questions all reveal his stance on both foreign and domestic policy.
- Lyndon Baines Johnson's State of The Union speech, 1964 January 08; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 9)
  President Johnson addresses congress with many prominent issues and offers his ideas in solving these issues. Among the many domestic and foreign issues he discusses are: civil rights, health needs of the elderly, tax cuts, transit policies, building schools homes and libraries, the war on poverty, social security, immigration, and strengthening Americas alliances. He continues his discussion by pledging to a progressive administration that will address these issues. President Johnson closes his speech with a brief tribute to John F. Kennedy.
- The inauguration of Lyndon Baines Johnson, 1965 January 20; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 10)
  The Inauguration of Lyndon B. Johnson was opened with the musical number Stars and Stripes Forever preformed by the U.S Marine Core Band and the Tabernacle Choir. This was followed by an Invocation by Reverend George R. Davis. After the Chief Justice Earl Warren administered the Oath of Office to Lyndon B. Johnson, President Johnson spoke of justice, liberty, the Union in his Inaugural Address.
- Special assignment: pornography, undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 11)
  In this KHJ broadcasting Special Assignment, Allan Moll conducts an interview with James Clancy, the former Deputy District Attorney who was assigned to obscenity cases. James Clancy reviews the nature of obscenity laws, compares the national standards to community standards and discusses with Allan the difference between hardcore pornography and erotic realism in literature as well as in other forms of the media. Then they discuss the role that congress, the police force and the public play in maintaining morality without infringing on human rights.
- The death of Eddie Cantor, 1964 October 10; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 12)
  To pay tribute to Eddie Cantor who died at age seventy-two, KHJ broadcasting airs excerpts of Bill Bradley conducting an interview with Eddie Cantor. The complete interview can be found in the Archives Museum in Hollywood. Eddie begins by describing how he began his career in show business and how much everything had changed since then. He defines "good" comedy and discusses his accomplishments and ambitions as an entertainer. He then goes on to share his opinion on the future of entertainment. This tribute is brought to a close with a recording of Eddie Cantor singing Aida.
- 1964 elections: KHJ election results, 1966 November 08; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 13)
  Allan Molls invites special guest Judd Lathen, former Chairman of the G.O.P Central Comity, to discuss election results. In discussing these results, Ted Myers reports on the national round up, George Brown discusses concession, Allan Moll reports on information from the field reporters located at Governor Browns headquarters, and Art Kevin reports on figures at the Local level, Assembly level, State Senate level, and at the Congressional level.
- Historic flight of Gemini, 1965 March 24; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 14)
  Marv Rothschild and Art Thompson report on the return of the Gemini space shuttle. Their report contains excerpts from the phone call that President Johnson made to Virgil Grism and John Young, the two returning astronauts as well as excerpts from news broadcasts that where aired the day that Gemini launched into space. Also included are reports from Gemini control on experiments that where conducted during the first orbit, vehicle orbital adjustments, minor complications, and on the retro fire. In closing, Vice President Hubert Humphrey welcomes home the astronauts from the Cape Kennedy Mission Control Center.
- Hollywood special: Richard Brooks, 1962 October 28; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 15)
  This is the third interview in the Hollywood Special series. These series contain provocative and objective discussions with outstanding film personalities on the position of the American motion picture in a changing world of revolutionary transformations from war, scientific advancement, as well as developing skills in the arts. In this particular interview, Richard Brooks discusses with Allan Moll his past, present and future accomplishments and his experiences with taking risks as a film director. He also discusses the Hollywood star system and the highly controversial issue of how Hollywood portrays America through film.
- Special assignment: pornography, 1965 January 21; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 16)
  In this Special Assignment, Art Kevin conducts an interview with Captain Walter Howell and Ernest E. Debbs. Walter Howell discusses the problems that policemen face when trying to make convictions in the vice squad and compares the regulations on modeling studios located in the city as opposed to the county. He also discusses the typical sentencing for prostitution and explains other areas of crime that the vice squad deals with. Ernest E. Debbs discusses the legality of the existence of modeling studios and book and movie stores, the publics' reaction to the existence of such places and explains the process of changing laws to maintain the moral fabric of society.
- 1964 elections: election aftermath, 1964 November 15; Reel-to-reel audiotape, audiocassette (Reel 17)
  This Audiotape was dubbed onto an Audiocassette due to very bad condition.
  This is the eighth and final show in a series of election coverage in which Allan Moll interviews Judge Romney and RKO General Broadcastings' analyst and pollster, Samuel Lubell. In these interviews, issues such as defense spending, the republican struggle and conservative philosophies are discussed. In addition to these interviews, Don Stevens reports on the party votes.
- 1964 elections: presidential primary elections, Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 18)
  In this election coverage series, Allan Moll reports from Los Angeles, Carlton Cordell reports from San Francisco, and Norm Woodruff reports from a RKO General Broadcasting mobile unit. Allan Moll introduces the leading candidates for the Presidential elections and the U.S Senate nominations as well as reviews the round up of the percentage of voters in the bay area and the facts about the G.O.P convention. Then Ben Hyte, a registrar of Los Angeles county voting, briefly takes us behind the scenes of voting. Norm Woodruff interviews voters as they exit the booths and recaps their views of the candidates. Carlton Cordell reports on the professional polling organization and Samuel Lubell analyses reports from the Goldwater headquarters in Los Angeles and from the Rockefeller headquarters in San Francisco and predicts the out come of the race. In closing, Allan Moll reviews the early returns.
- 1964 elections: presidential primary elections, undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 19)
  Allan Moll, Samuel Lubell, and George Brown discuss the difference between expressing an opinion of the outcome of a race and projecting the outcome of a race. They then go on to discuss the late associated press returns including Presidential and Senatorial results, and the voters' views of the candidates. In an interview with Senator Javits they compare the republican platform for 1960 and 1964 and discuss party unity. Cliff Engle reports on the Bay Area snap tallies from City Hall in San Francisco then the coverage is brought to a close with a statement from Rockefeller followed by questions from the press.
- 1964 elections: convention preview, 1964 July 12; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 20)
  RKO General Broadcasting newsmen preview the 1964 Republican National Convention in Atlantic City. Lester Smith reports on the New York, New Jersey and Pennsylvania delegations, Al Benjamin and Bill Whelan report on the New England delegations, Don Stevens covers the Dixie delegations, Austin Grant covers the Mid-western delegations, Allan Moll covers the delegations of the Western states, and Carlton Cordell covers the Northwest delegations. Their guests include Ralph Goldwin, a Prophesier of Political Science, and Samuel Lubell, a pollster and political analyst. After reporting on the delegations, each newsman predicts the outcome of the November elections in their designated areas.
- 1964 elections: who is ahead, 1964 October 11; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 21)
  This is the sixth in a series of eight election coverage specials. Each reporter is assigned to a different area of the Country where he reports on the areas response to different political issues and to the candidates. Lester Smith reports on New York, New Jersey and Pennsylvania, Al Benjamin reports on Boston, Don Stevens reports on the Southern states, Austin Grant covers the Midwest, Allan Moll covers South California and John Holbrook covers the Northwest. Some of the issues that are covered include white front lash and backlash, civil rights, employment and national issues such as communism, world peace, freedom, the defense industry, and nuclear weapons. Allan Moll and Carlton Cordell summarize which candidate is ahead in which areas, which is then analyzed by Samuel Lubell.
- Goldwater interview, 1964; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 22)
  In this interview, Goldwater discusses the California Primary, the July Republican convention in San Francisco, his relations with Rockefeller and domestic and foreign issues. A few of the domestic and foreign issues that he shares his view on are civil rights and the Rumford Act, the prospect of a Cuban invasion, and the Vietnam War. He then discusses how foreign policy effects the November elections.
- 1964 elections: Governor Knight and Samuel Lubell, Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 23)
  This election coverage starts out with a review and analysis of the projections and results and is followed by an interview with Rockefellers campaign manager. This is followed by a report from Goldwater headquarters in which Goldwater thanks his supporters and claims a victory for the republicans and the grass roots movement. Following this is a press conference with senator Goldwater live from the Ambassador hotel. In closing, Allan Moll, Samuel Lubell, and George Brown discuss the "stop Goldwater movement" and Samuel Lubell explains the different methods of projecting the outcome of a race and on what basis these projections are made.
- 1964 elections: politics, 1964 April 08; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 24)
  In this analysis of the 1964 elections, Samuel Lubell gives us an inside look at the polls and the significance of the primary elections. In doing this, he explains the different methods that he uses when interviewing voters and explains the process of coming up with accurate projections. In closing Allan Moll reviews the facts that one should know when voting in California including eligibility and when and how to vote.
- President Johnson's congressional address shortly after John F. Kennedy's death, 1963 November 27; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 25)
  Mutual Broadcasting Systems brings us live and direct coverage from the House of Representatives. Presidents Johnson opens his address with a brief tribute to John F. Kennedy in which he urges congressmen to continue on with President Kennedys domestic movements. He then moves onto foreign policies discussing the national interest, national action and expansion of foreign trade. After President Johnsons address, an excerpt from America the Beautiful is aired.
- Insanity and the law, 1964 May 10; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 26)
  In this program, Allan Moll discusses insanity and how the law deals with it with former Governor Goodwin Knight, Melvin Belli, one of the council members for the Jack Ruby trial, Assistant District Attorney Lynn Compton, Chief of Police Parker, and Dr. Lawrence Freedman. They discuss the history of the McNaughtin ruling, temporary insanity verses voluntary manslaughter, granting clemency and the function of physiatrists in criminal cases.
- Viewpoint Los Angeles: interview with Governor Pat Brown, 1965 January 03; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 27)
  In this interview Governor Pat Brown shares his views on reapportionment, on Senator Kiko running for Governor, and the defeat of Pier Salinger. He discusses taxes in California and the split in the Democratic Party. He goes on to discuss his personal interest in the United States Senate and the Supreme Court.
- Start of the Watts Riots - first bulletin, Gemini VIII, 1965; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 28)
  Allan Moll reports on the beginning of the Watts Riots on KHJ Radio. In this coverage is the number of injuries caused by the riots and the different forms of violence used, what factors went into the cause of the riots, who was involved and the police forces response to the riots.
  Next on this Audiotape is a report on the Gemini VIII space shuttle. This coverage begins with an excerpt from an interview with Major Scott at the NASA news conference in which Major Scott discusses some of the training required for E.V.A, required equipment and their functions, and contact dynamics.
- The Academy Awards, 1964 April 05; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 29)
  This Audiotape contains Allan Moll briefly interviewing the following stars on the night of the Academy Awards: Steve McQueen, Claudia Cardinelli, Angela Lansbury, Johnny Winters, Rear Garson, Rosalyn Russell, Vince Edwards, Merrill Oberon, Carl Molden, Erb Cubsonate, Rock Hudson, Arlene Doll, Elizabeth Ashley, Julie Andrews, Audrey Hepburn, Gladis Cooper and Rex Harrison.
- Hollywood Special: interview with Jimmy Stewart, 1962 October 21; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 30)
  In this Hollywood Special Allan Moll interviews actor James Stewart who discusses Hollywood film production after World War II, the basic problems that the acting industry faces, and his personal acting history. He also discusses controversial issues such as the Star System, the American image overseas and how the Hollywood film industry effects that image, the future of Hollywood and paid television, run away productions, and actors who switch over to directing or producing movies.
- Hollywood special: interview with Janet Leigh, 1962 November 08; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 31)
  In this interview conducted by Allan Moll, actress Janet Leigh discusses the role of cinema, Americas image overseas and how Hollywood cinema effects that image, the responsibilities of a producer, Independent films, what it takes to make a blockbuster hit, and the future of Hollywood. She also discusses how being a star has effected her personal life as well as her views on paid television and runaway productions.
- Liftoff of Mercury, 1963 May 20; Reel-to-reel audiotape, audiocassette (Reel 32)
  This Audiotape was dubbed onto an Audiocassette due to bad condition.
  This is a report from Mercury Control at the time of the Mercury space shuttles liftoff.
- Interview with James Roosevelt, January 10; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 33)
  In this interview conducted by Allan Moll, James Roosevelt, Franklin D. Roosevelts son and congressman form the twenty-sixth congressional district, announces his candidacy for the Mayor of Los Angeles. He discusses his views on the influx of so many candidates into the mayoralty race, his relationship with Congressman Bell, politicians who hold one office while running for another, the antiquated city charter, and the role of Mayor. He also discusses his experiences as a congressman, his reasons for running for Mayor, the fight between the Mayor and the city regarding the Whyman machine, his stand on the House of American Activities committee and national issues such as air pollution, Education, and taxation.
- Hollywood Special: interview with Harold Lloyd, undated; Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 34)
  In this interview conducted by Allan Moll, Harold Lloyd, a film comedian from the 1920s and 1930s, discusses the role of entertainment, the differences between low budget and high budget films, Americas image overseas and how Hollywood cinema effects that image, and the future of Hollywood. He goes on to discuss his views on the Hollywood star system, the trend of Actors becoming directors or producers, runaway film productions, and his personal interests.
- 1965 World Series playback with Sandy Koufax, Reel-to-reel audiotape (Reel 35)